Finding Aid for Heber Doust Curtis papers, 1889-1890, 1900-1908, and 1921-1942
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Heber Doust Curtis papers 1889-1890, 1900-1908, 1921-1942
Curtis, Heber Doust, 1872-1942.
1.3 linear foot
851268 Aa 2
Professor of astronomy at University of Michigan. Personal correspondence, mainly with family, describing his various astronomical expeditions to Chile and Sumatra; also speeches and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was acquired in 1950 (donor no. 4371 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Heber Doust Curtis was born June 27, 1892 in Muskegon, Michigan. He received his A.B. (1892) and A.M. (1893) degrees from the University of Michigan. Prior to receiving his Ph.D. from the University of Virginia, Curtis taught Latin at Napa College (1894-1897) and mathematics and astronomy at the University of the Pacific, 1897-1900. He came to the University of Virginia as Fellow in Astronomy, 1900-1902; then became Assistant, 1902-1904. From 1904 to 1910, Curtis was in Santiago, Chile, as assistant, then as astronomer in charge of the Lick Observatory station, three years of which he headed the D.O. Mills Expedition to the Southern Hemisphere, 1906-1909. He left the Lick Observatory in 1920 to become Director of the Allegheny Observatory. In 1930 he came to the University of Michigan as professor of astronomy, chairman of the Department of Astronomy and Director o the Observatories. As an astronomer, Curtis was renowned as a specialist in solar eclipses and celestial photography. He died January 9, 1942.
The collection consists mainly of copies of letters to family describing his work in astronomy, trips to Mexico, Sumatra and Europe and comments on current events with frequent references to personal family matters. There is one letter, July 19, 1925, concerning the teaching of evolution in the schools with comments about Clarence Darrow, William Jennings Bryan, and the Scopes trial.
Subjects:
Astronomy.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Chile.; Curtis, Heber Doust, 1872-1942.; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.; Evolution--Religious aspects.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Sumatra (Indonesia); University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Astronomical observatories.; Astronomy.; Children.; Chile.; Curtis, Heber Doust, 1872-1942.; Eclipses.; Indonesia.; Maine.; Mexico.; Nevada.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Soviet Union.; University of Michigan. Class of 1893.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  (mainly carbons of outgoing letters to family)
  - 1900-1908 1921-1942, 23 folders (Box 1)
- Bound correspondence volumes 1918-1940
  - "Points West" 1918-1923 (Box 1)
  - "And Points East" 1925-1932 (Box 1)
  - "Way Stations" 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - "Alarums and Excursions" 1937-1940 (Box 1)
- Speeches, 1 folders
  - "Astronomy and Modern Thought" June 3, 1931 (Box 1)
  - "Does Life Exist Elsewhere?" November 4, 1934 (Box 1)
  - "Intolerance in Science" (Box 1)
  - "Island Universes" November 4, 1920 (Box 1)
  - "The Influence of Astronomy Upon Modern Thought" February 10, 1928 (Box 1)
  - "The Influence of Astronomy Upon Modern Thought" December 5, 1933 (Box 1)
  - "Log Reading 33.5" (Box 1)
  - "1902-1932-1962" (Box 1)
  - "On the Unity of the Universe" January 10, 1927 (Box 1)
  - "Receding Horizons" Henry Russell Lecture 1938 (Box 1)
  - "Reminiscences of a Pittsburgh Astronomer in the 20's" (Box 1)
  - "The Relation of the Modern Physical Sciences to Religion" (Box 1)
  - "Religion from the Standpoint of Science" November 19, 1928 (Box 1)
  - "The Scientist Looks at Religion" (Box 1)
  - "The Scientist's Right to Religious Speculation" (Box 1)
  - "Some Thoughts on Religious Education" (Box 1)
- Miscellanea
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Greek notebook (Box 1)
  - Clippings and other materials largely relating to eclipses (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes images from eclipse expeditions to Sumatra (1901, 1926, 1929), Mexico (1923), Nevada (1930), Maine (1932), and other places and photos of visits to the Philippines (on Sumatra trips) and Chile. The series also includes portraits and photos of various professional groups.
  - Chile (Box 1)
  - Eclipse Expeditions
    - 1900, Thomaston, GA (Box 1)
    - 1905, Cartwright, Labrador (Box 1)
    - 1914, Kiev Russia (Box 1)
    - 1918, Goldendale, Wash. (Box 1)
    - 1923, Yerbaniz, Mexico (Box 1)
    - 1926, Beukoelen, Sumatra, and 1929 Takengon, Sumatra (Box 1)
      (includes loose photos from 1926 Sumatra album)
    - 1930, Gerlach, Nev. (Box 1)
    - 1932, Freiburg, Me. (Box 1)
  - Groups (Box 1)
  - Loose photos from 1901 Sumatra album (Box 1)
  - Observatories and other buildings (Box 1)
  - Photos/Portraits, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Albums
    - U.S. Naval Observatory Expedition to observe the total solar eclipse of May 18, 1901 in Sumatra (Box 2)
    - Sumatra expedition 1926 (Box 2)
    - Loose pages from Chile album (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous album pages (Box 2)
Related Material
Other files of Heber D. Curtis are located at the Mary Lea Shane Archives of the Lick Observatory, University of California, Santa Cruz, California.